Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim.
This is Geshe Michael Roach.
And what's that lady thinking about?
Let's go to the Tibetan
text of the Lam Rim.
ZHES SOGS KYI RIGS PA GCIG
LAS MED PAS RTOGS DKA' LA
It means and if you think about it,
I think we can feel it together
that to really believe in a past life,
it's difficult, it's just difficult.
We get wrapped up in this life.
We're focused on this life,
and this life is so busy.
There's so many things going on,
and it's so concrete, it's
here, we can't deny it.
Then somebody says, "Well,
did you have a past life?"
And you're like, "Look, maybe,
I don't have time to think about it now."
Then, I think all of us,
we avoid difficult ideas.
We don't like to think about
things that are difficult to figure out.
So I think most of us,
we avoid this question
of did we have a past life?
I have to say that Dharmakirti proved
that there was a past life.
It was a difficult proof.
There were different parts to it.
But the basic idea is,
something to think about,
is that according to Buddhism
and according to truth, really,
life cannot be created from
that which is not alive.
Life cannot come from
a cause which is not similar to life.
You don't get apples from pineapples.
What?
That's not so good.
Bananas from rice.
It doesn't happen.
You don't get awareness of consciousness
from something other than consciousness.
That's mainly the whole thing.
That's mainly the whole idea.
What Dharmakirti was saying,
and it was so difficult that I think
maybe we didn't feel it, was
that you can't take a stone
and turn it into life.
Life, there's living flesh
and flesh is imbued with life,
and that flesh comes from chemicals.
But the life part in the
flesh comes from life,
and therefore we must have had life
just before we were
conceived in this life.
All right so we're...
Here it says
RIGS PA GCIG LAS MED PAS RTOGS DKA'
That's where we see the
young lady having difficulty
thinking about...
RTOGS DKA' means look, it's difficult.
Remember he compared
it to seeing emptiness.
It's on the level of
difficulty of seeing emptiness.
It's difficult to think,
where did I come from?
'DI LA DANG PO RIG PA'I YA MTHA'
THUG MED DU BSGRUB DGOS PAS
This RIG PA, in fact, I corrected it
and then I uncorrected it.
This RIG PA does mean your mind stream.
It doesn't mean logic
or clear thinking that's
RIGS PA
RIG PA'I YA MTHA' THUG MED DU BSGRUB DGOS
You must prove
BSGRUB PA
DGOS means you must prove
that your mind has had
no beginning.
You cannot point to a beginning.
YA MTHA' THUG MED means
'THUG MED means that you never will hit
a beginning point.
YA MTHA' means if you go looking for
the first moment of awareness,
the first moment of Michael's
awareness in history,
you will never find it.
Look at this lady's face.
It's something we're
supposed to think about.
It's difficult. It's just hard.
What I've learned in a long life is that
when things are hard to
understand, then you have to stop
and you have to try to
understand. You have to stop.
I study scriptures a lot
and I worked very, very
hard on them. I just,
over many years time, I got into a habit
that my teacher taught
me, and you just stop.
You figure it out. You don't skip it.
And you don't go ahead and
if it takes you three
days to figure it out,
then you spend three days on
it because it's important.
DE RING GI SEMS 'DI KHA SANG
GI SEMS KYI RGYUN YIN ZHING
DE RING GI SEMS means your mind of today.
KHA SANG GI SEMS means
your mind of yesterday.
RGYUN means is the flow.
Your present thoughts are
the flow or the stream
of yesterday's thoughts continuing.
DE'ANG KHA NYIN GYI RIG
RGYUN YIN PA NAS BZUNG
And yesterday's thoughts are KHA NYIN.
KHA NYIN means KHES NYIN
PA in colloquial Tibetan,
means the day before yesterday.
So yesterday's thoughts are
the continuation of the flow
of the thoughts of the day before.
YIN PA NAS BZUNG means
and you can track it back,
you can track it back.
MA'I MNGAL NAS SKYES MA THAG PA'I SEMS
You can go back to the
state of mind you had
just after you came out
of your mother's womb.
MNGAL NAS SKYES
Don't forget, in Buddhism there's
two kinds of birth, SKYES.
One is MNGAL NAS SKYES, which is here,
when you actually come
out of your mother's womb,
but technically in Buddhism,
the moment of conception
is the beginning of this
birth, of this rebirth.
SKYES MA THAG PA'I SEMS
So if you go back to the
state of mind you had
on the day that you came out
of your mom in the hospital,
SKYE KHA MA'I RGYUN YIN ZHING
that's the,
what your mind today can be traced back
to the state of mind you had.
SKYE KHA MA means just
after you were born,
at the moment of birth. But
MNGAL DU ZHUGS MA THAG PA'I SEMS DE
but you can also track that
back to the mind you had.
This ZHUGS is the past tense of 'JUG
which means when you
entered your mom's womb.
So the state of mind that you had
on the day you came out of
your mom in the hospital
is really the continuation of the flow
of the mind which entered
your mother's womb,
nine months and 10 days before.
MNGAL MA THAG PA'I SEMS DE ZHUGS KHA MA'I
RIG PA'I RGYUN YIN PA'I PHYIR
So you can trace your mind back to...
All scientists would agree,
all westerners would agree
that you can trace your
stream of mind back to
the moment after you entered the womb.
Now, if you existed before
that, that's a debate,
but nobody would say you
cannot trace this consciousness
back to the womb.
'KHOR BA LA THOG MA'I MTHA' MED PAS
SEMS KYI 'GO BRTZOM PA 'DI'O, ,ZHES PA
'KHOR BA LA THOG MA'I MTHA' MED PA means
THOG MA means beginning.
MTHA' means front-end.
So the front-end of your
lives, of your rebirth,
MTHA' MED
you can't point to a certain
point at which you started,
where your lifetimes
in this circle started.
The name for this life is
sansara, which means a circle.
It means that, as soon
as you finish one life,
you picking up on another life,
and then you pick up on another life,
and then it's a circle.
'GO BRTZOM PA 'DI'O,
This 'GO is spelled 'a-o ga naro' 'GO
which doesn't mean head.
If it's 'ma-o ga naro'
MGO, M-G-O, it means head.
This 'GO means to begin.
So 'GO BRTZOM PA means you
cannot point to a certain point
in time, in history, and say
that was the beginning of my mind.
ZHIG GANG DU'ANG MI RNYED PAS
You won't be able to find it.
By the way, this find is
the same verb that we use
when you go looking for an object
which is not coming from you.
When you talk about two
husbands in a kitchen
and you try to find a husband
that's not coming from you,
that's called RNYED, same verb.
You can attempt to
locate, it's called RNYED.
You can go looking for a husband
who's not coming from you,
but you won't find it.
You can go looking for a first
moment of your awareness,
of your consciousness,
but you won't find it.
RANG GI SKYE BA LA'ANG THOG MA'I MTHA' MED
Therefore, because
there's no beginning point
of the river of your mind,
therefore, there's no first
birth that you ever had.
Because if there's no
beginning point of the river
or the flow of your mind,
then there's no first birth either.
MTHA' MED PAR GRUB LA
And this is an old argument
which I've described to
you many times, but...
I was brought up in school,
when I was taught in school,
we were taught that things
should have a beginning
ཊhen they teach us the Big Bang
But if you think careful about it,
the idea of a first beginning,
is illogical. It's not logical.
It's comfortable to us
because we grew up with it.
Oftentimes when you teach people
that sansara has no beginning,
it feels uncomfortable to them
if they learned something else in school,
when they're a kid. But if you say,
look, you're not a kid
anymore, now you're grown up,
now you have to think for yourself.
Does it make sense that
everything has a cause,
except the first thing of everything?
That doesn't make sense, come on.
Then once you grow up, you
have to give up this idea
that a beginning is more logical
because it's not more
logical, it's illogical.
It's illogical
that something which goes
on in a flow for 68 years
should have a beginning
where it didn't have a flow.
That doesn't make sense.
THOG MA'I MTHA' MED PAR GRUB LA
You can prove
that there's no beginning
to the flow of your mind.
DE GRUB PAS SKYE BA GRANGS KYIS MI CHOD PA
ZHIG YOD PAR GRUB PAS
If you prove that the flow
or the river of your thoughts
or your awareness never had a beginning,
then by implication,
you prove that you have
never had a first birth.
You have never had a first rebirth.
GRUB PAS SKYE BA LA YA MTHA' MED
Therefore, there is no beginning point
to the process of you being born.
Die, born, die, born,
die, born, die, born.
There's no beginning to that.
All right, I like this image.
I was trying to...
My job, part of my job,
when I prepare for a Lam Rim
teaching is to find pictures
or images that can help
you remember the ideas.
Again, these are IDIMS, idea images and
it's good for you.
Traditionally in the Lam Rim
you're supposed to review three times.
Right after you get home,
after you'd listened to this,
you're supposed to close your
eyes and review everything.
Then that evening, you're
supposed to review again.
And then the next morning,
you're supposed to review again.
I'm trying to find photographs or images
that will help you review.
So an easy way to review the Lam Rim,
what you're supposed
to do if you want it to
affect your mind.
A great thing to do
is to go through the pictures
that I'm showing you.
When you finish the class,
right after you finish the
class, go through the pictures.
Do you remember what
that picture represents?
Pao, what's the picture of the lady
going like this represent?
Or Gyelse? Venerable Gyelse.
Why is she? That was
the first picture today.
[Student] Thinking about past life.
Yeah, she's trying to figure it out.
Did I have a past life or
didn't I have a past life?
Don't say you figured it out easily
because if you did, you didn't.
It's difficult. It's
really, really, really hard.
So when you see that picture I
want you to think about that.
Now, the picture I'm talking about now,
is this, I don't know,
it's an ocean or something,
with an ouroboros.
I don't know how to
pronounce it, ouroboros.
Yeah, I like these two images.
I put these two images together.
That a snake eating its tail is called,
I don't know how to
pronounce it, ouroboros?
It represents
a cycle that continues upon itself.
A circle which,
an ending which becomes a beginning.
Can you keep the image up?
I'm going to talk about it.
Yeah, good, thank you Pachi.
So I'm thinking of the water in the lake:
how it sits in the lake,
then it evaporates,
then it becomes a cloud,
then the cloud runs around,
then the cloud turns into rain,
the rain falls in the
lake, and it's a cycle
similar to the snake
that's eating its tail.
By the way, I like
languages and I looked up,
what's the root of ouroboros.
[Student] Ouroboros.
Ouroboros, okay.
And it's very interesting.
'Boros' means to eat.
It's got a lot of roots in Russian.
'бороться' means fight with a sword.
And Boris comes from that
because it's a sword fighter.
So 'бороться' means to fight
with swords and chop up things.
'Ouru' comes from 'ors' which became arse,
which means your ass.
I thought it was so cute.
So arse eater, arse chopper.
Arse chopper with your teeth
means the snake that eats its own tail.
I think it's a nice image,
a nice Irish image for
things that perpetuate themselves.
Self-perpetuating cycles.
I think it's a perfect
picture in the way that
rain becomes lakes, lakes become clouds
and clouds become rain.
DAS NA TSE 'DI'I AA MA YOD PA BZHIN DU
TSE SNGA MA'I MNGAL SKYES
DANG SGONG SKYE GNYIS
DES NA
Therefore,
TSE 'DI'I AA MA
There's a joke.
When I was trying to get
into a Tibetan class,
when I first started Tibetan.
The teacher wanted me to be in the class,
but there was this
administrator to the college
that didn't want me to be in the class.
They agreed that they would test me
with some Tibetan words to see
if I could get in the class.
So I went into the test.
I was really nervous
because I knew like five words.
And the guy who wanted
me in the class, he said,
"Okay, what is AA MA and AA PHA mean?
I said, "Mom and Dad?"
He said, "Correct, you're in the class."
The other guy was really irritated.
DES NA AA MA YOD PA BZHIN DU means
you had an AA MA, you
had a mom in this life.
BZHIN DU TSE SNGA MA'I
MNGAL SKYE DANG SGONG SKYES
Now he says,
$50 question for the advanced
students in the room.
He says, with reference
to birth from a womb
and to birth from an egg.
Why does he say that?
With reference to birth from
the womb and birth from an egg.
[Student] You can say the
two did come from a mother.
Yeah, good, yeah!
How many kinds of births
are there in total?
Four.
According to Buddhism and by the way,
this is one of the first
teachings of the Buddha.
It's considered a big part
of the first turning of the wheel,
that there's four ways to take
birth. What's the other two?
DROD GSHER LAS SKYE BA which means,
when mosquitoes are
born from warm water and
warm water -- DROD GSHER
because they didn't know
they were eggs in there,
and they were too small to see.
What's the other one?
RDZUS TE SKYE
Where you born in a lotus
or like Patanjali, he's
born in his mother's hands.
It's interesting that
Pabongka is a great debater,
although he was a very gentle person
and a very kind teacher,
he wasn't this kind of
arrogant debater type.
But he's covering his ass.
By the way with reference
to two kinds of birth.
SKABS KYI AA MA RE DGOS PAS
You got to have AA MA RE.
RE RE means each.
For each birth there has to be a mom.
Each birth has to have
a corresponding mother.
So the RE is very important here.
DGOS PAS
You got to have
DE 'DRA'I SKYE BA GCIG LEN PA LA
Therefore, if you have one birth,
which is one of those two kinds
from the womb or from the eggs,
you got to have one mom each.
AA MA GCIC DGOS PA BZHIN DU
By the way, in a debate, if you agree,
it's like a chess game. The
guy's going to set you up.
In the beginning he'll look very innocent.
He'll move a pawn
and then suddenly you realize
he trapped you already.
With the first two moves or three moves.
In a debate you're like, "Okay,
if you're born from a womb,
each birth needs a mom, right?"
And so, just one each, right?
Then you're already
committed to countless moms.
Just one each, right?
One each, I don't have
a problem with that.
SKYE BA BRGYA LEN PA NA
If you take a 100 births,
then you got to have MA
BRGYA. What's that mean?
You got to have 100 mothers,
100 births, 100 mothers.
Hey, you agreed, one-to-one.
STONG LEN PA NA MA STONG
If you take a 1000 rebirths,
then you got a thousand moms.
Therefore, GRANGS MED DGOS
It must be, you know
this GRANGS from Sankhya,
GRANGS CAN BA
The count must be, it must be countless.
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD KYIS
MA MA BYAS PA'I THABS MED
Double negative, the first MA is mom.
Now there's two negatives,
what's that mean?
MA MA BYAS PA'I THABS MED, MA MA MED
MA MA MED
There's nobody who hasn't been your mom.
MA MA BYAS PA'I THABS MED
There's no way anyone
has not been your mom.
You agreed one-to-one: one birth one mom.
Countless births, countless moms.
Therefore, everyone's been your mom.
I like this picture. I call
it, It's just the odds.
I found this photo, I like it.
It's the numbers coming
out of this guy's hands.
And it's just math.
Do you agree that to have one--
Do you agree that to be born
once you have to have a mom?
Yes, I agree. Then, you
agree to countless moms.
Everyone's been your mother.
It's just mathematics. It's
not Buddhism. It's math.
DE LA 'DI LTAR, AA MA MANG DU DGOS MOD,
SEMS CAN NI MTHA' YAS PAS DE THAMS CAD NI
AA MA CANG MIN NO ZHE NA
Now, Pabongka starts to
present the natural objections
that come up in your mind to these ideas.
The minute I say,
is there one mom required for each birth?
- Yes. - Have you had countless births?
- Yes. - Well then, do
you have countless moms?
- No.
Then you say, What? But you have to.
And you say, no, no.
Geshe-la, the Buddhism says many times
that living beings are countless.
Living beings are countless.
I understand one-on-one, I understand, but
how many for countless?
Living beings are countless.
How can everyone be my mom?
SPYIR RANG GI SKYE BA MANG
BAR MA ZAD KYI; BYE BRAG
And then he gets--
Instead of answering the question,
he kills the guy with more information.
He goes deeper. He says,
"Look, forget your question.
Let's talk about the
different kinds of beings."
SPYIR RANG GI SKYE BA MANG BAR MA ZAD
You've had lots of moms, you want to say
not countless, I don't
care, that's all right.
But, BYE BRAG, okay? Here's SPYI BYE BRAG.
At the beginning of the
sentence is SPYI with a R,
and then BYE BRAG.
SPYIR means generally speaking,
you had lots of moms.
But more particularly,
let's talk about wild animals.
RI DVAGS means wild animals.
Animals of the wild, of the wilderness.
For example, SHA BA means a deer,
and DGO BA means an antelope.
'BU SRIN means bugs, insects, ants,
grasshoppers, 'BU SRIN
SOGS RE RE NAS KYI LUS
BLANGS PA'ANG GRANGS MED CING
The number of times you have put on
a grasshopper body are countless.
How do you say grasshopper
in Spanish? I'm curious.
[Student] Saltamontes.
Saltamontes? Oh cool.
What's salta?
[Student] Jump.
Jump, mountain jumper?
Saltamontes, okay cool.
Saltamontes, so you
have been a saltamontes.
LUS BLANGS PA'ANG GRANGS MED
The times you have been just a
grasshopper, not other being,
just a grasshopper, is also countless.
Forget the human rebirth.
The times you have been a
grasshopper has been
countless, saltamontes.
DE LTAR SEMS CAN GYI RIGS GRANGS MED PA
The different types of
beings are countless.
The different species of beings
are countless. Therefore,
SEMS CAN GYI RIGS GRANGS
MED PA RE RE'I 'ANG
among those countless species
you have taken countless births
in each one of the countless species.
So how many births is that, please?
Countless times countless.
GRANGS MED PA BLANGS PA'I
PHYIR, SEMS CAN LAS KYANG
GRANGS MANG BA'I SKYE BA BLANGS LA
Therefore, you have taken more births
than the number of living
beings in the universe.
Because they're just stuck
in one form of life now,
but you have to multiply
that times countless.
Don't tell me,
Geshe-la, there's countless
beings in the universe.
I agree. But don't forget
each countless being
had countless rebirths
as this grasshopper.
That's countless times
countless times countless.
Don't tell me they haven't been your mom.
Okay, it's kind of cool.
DE'I TSE NA AA MA'ANG
GRANGS DE MTSUNGS DGOS PAS
Each time you were born as a grasshopper,
we got a bug here, we've got a worm here.
You got a picture of a worm?
I think so.
I'm thinking about worms
because it's springtime.
I'm working in my garden. I'm
trying not to hurt the worms.
They say they survive if you cut them.
Each half survives and becomes a worm.
But I just keep thinking about,
would I like to be cut in half?
Then I say, no. So I try to
avoid, I try to help them.
And then,
you've had countless
rebirths just as a worm.
You've had countless
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD KYIS
AA MA BYAS PA TZAM MA ZAD
Not only has every living
being been your mother
but they have been your
mother countless times
in each of the countless forms of life.
Everybody has been your mother as a worm,
countless times.
And then multiply that times
how many different life forms are there.
That's how many moms you've had.
YIN NO
Then he quotes a very
beautiful book by Nagarjuna.
It's one of the two books
I'm thinking to give a friend of mine,
because it's a extremely valuable book
and it's probably the first
Lam Rim, which is BSHES SPRING
Letter to a Friend, Suhṛllekha.
Which is really suhṛd lekha
and the D changes to L.
suhṛd means good heart,
and lekha means an epistle,
which comes from rekhā,
which means to scratch something.
Anyway, BSHES SPRING
means Letter to a Friend.
And Nagarjuna wrote a letter to
a king named Udayabhadra,
if I'm not mistaken.
That would be a great text to translate.
MA YI THUG MTHA' RGYA SHUG TSI GU TZAM
MA YI THUG MTHA'
means establishing the ultimate
number of moms you've had,
could be illustrated by RGYA SHUG TSI GU.
RGYA SHUG means a juniper
tree and we have them,
tens of thousands around here.
Which I like, I like them, I
think they're beautiful and
they give everybody allergies.
TSI GU means a small ball that you make,
like a small ball of,
like if you take some mud
and you make a tiny ball
out of it. That's called a TSI GU.
ZHES SOGS KYI DNGOS BSTAN MA'I MA,
DE'I MA SOGS LA SBYAR YANG
Let's apply that statement from Nagarjuna
and that statement by
Nagarjuna is, if you sit
and you make,
if you sit on the ground
like a kid on a rainy day
and you make little balls of mud,
the size of a juniper berry,
how long would it take
to run out of planet?
How long would it take
to run out of the planet?
Pabongka Rinpoche says,
there's a tradition
that you don't count it the way it sounds.
You don't say this is my mom.
This person was my mom.
Then at the end of the planet,
you've counted up everything.
He says, that's not the real
point, the real point is,
the first ball, the first
juniper berry sized ball of mud
is this mom of this life.
And then there's the mom of this mom.
And then there's a moms of that mom.
And then there's the moms.
So it's exponential. He's
saying, that's the real teaching.
Because there is an end to the
balls of juniper berry
sized balls in the planet.
But there's no end, if you go exponential.
SBYAR YANG, SKABS 'DIR
BLA MA'I GSUNG RGYUN LTAR
KHA BSGYUR NAS
If we adjust this statement by Nagarjuna
to fit the oral tradition
around that statement.
GSUNG RGYUN means oral tradition.
KHA BSGYUR means if we adjust it
SA CHEN PO 'DI RGYA SHUG GI
TSI GU TZAM GYI RIL BUR BYAS
If we make tiny balls of mud
equal in the size of juniper berries
out of the whole planet,
SA CHEN PO 'DI RANG GI TSE 'DI'I MA
and then we say, this one
is my mother in this life,
and the second ball is my
mother in the life before that,
and a third ball is the mother
I had in the life before the life before.
RI LU RE
Then if you put those balls,
BZHAG means if you put them in a pile,
RDZOGS TE
you would reach an end.
The planet would,
the dirt in the planet would run out. But
MA'I GRANGS KYI BRGYA STONG
GI CHAR YANG MI 'GRO BAS
BRGYA CHA STONG CHA
means 1/100th or 1/1000th
MI 'GRO
It wouldn't represent 1/10th of 1%
of your mothers you've had.
You would run out of planet
and you wouldn't reach
0.001 of the mothers
you've had. Therefore,
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD KYIS
MA MA BYAS NA MI 'DANG BA
'DANG BA means to be sufficient.
'O MA 'DANG GI 'DUG GAM means
do we have enough milk to
give all the monks tea?
'DANG means to be sufficient.
He says you wouldn't have enough balls
to represent all the
mothers. You would run out.
It wouldn't--
SEMS CAN KUN GYIS MA GRANGS
MED RE MA BYAS NA MI 'DANG BAS
Unless every living being in the universe
has been your mother countless times,
the math doesn't work out.
The math doesn't work out.
The math is weird.
Unless every living being
has been your mother,
not once but countless times.
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD KYIS
RANG GI MA BYAS SHING,
RE RES KYANG MANG DU BYAS TE,
SEMS CAN 'DI'I LUS MA BLANGS
BYA BA MED, BLANGS PA LA
GRANGS KYIS MI CHOD TSUL BSAM,
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD KYIS RANG GI MA BYAS
You got to be--
So Tim, in this Lam Rim section,
you have to be careful with the MAs,
because generally they mean
not but here they mean mom.
But some of them mean not so
you got to be careful. So here,
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD KYIS RANG GI MA BYAS
Every living being has been your mother.
RE RES KYANG MANG DU BYAS TE
And each one has been
your mom countless times.
SEMS CAN 'DI'I LUS MA BLANGS BYA BA MED
You cannot say there is a body
of a life form that you have not taken.
There's no lifeform's body,
which you have not lived in.
You have dressed in the body
of every kind of insect,
every kind of whale, every kind of bird,
every kind of bacteria,
every kind of COVID virus.
You have been.
BLANGS BYA BA MED
BLANGS PA LA GRANGS KYIS MI CHOD TSUL BSAM
And there's no number.
There's no count of how
many times you took on
each of the different bodies.
DE'ANG MI'I SKYE BA
BLANGS PA LTA BUR MTSON NA
Then he says, you want to get deeper?
You guys want to go deep?
- [Students In Unison] Yes!
He says, you've been every kind of bug
countless times and
there's not enough mothers
to be your mother for those bugs,
unless it's been
everybody in the universe.
The math doesn't work out.
Moreover, DE'ANG, moreover,
let's just talk about the
times you were born as a human.
MI'I SKYE BA BLANGS PA LTA
BUR MTSON NA GLING 'DI'I SA
PHYOGS 'DIR MA SKYES BYA BA MED
You cannot point to a
square meter on this planet
that you have not been
born, in that square meter.
You cannot point to a
square meter in any country
on the earth of this world,
where you have not been born.
You cannot point to one.
SKYES BYA BA MED, SKYES
PA LA GRANGS KYIS MI CHOD
In fact, I don't know, pick
a place in Guadalajara.
We talked about Aldo's neighborhood.
The corner of the street
that Aldo lives on,
that meter, you have been
born there countless times.
You have been born in that square meter
of this planet countless times.
DE BZHIN DU SHAR LHO NUB BYANG
East, South, West, North.
I don't care what directions.
I don't care what
country, forget countries.
There's not a square inch where
you haven't been born before
and countless times.
And by the way, this world
only lasted, I don't know,
5 billion years or something?
It doesn't matter.
He's talking about the
dirt that you were born on.
You've been born on that dirt
countless times and that dirt
has wandered around to different
planets countless times.
'JIG RTEN RE RE LA'ANG GRANGS MED PA
The worlds you have been
born on are countless.
RE BLANGS PAS, SEMS CAN
LAS KYANG MANG BA'I PHYIR
The number of planets you've
been born on countless times,
exceeds the countless number of beings.
Therefore, you have been everybody's kid
countless times.
I made this little
picture, you guys ready?
I like this cute little
picture of our world.
Somehow, I got it with
animals on it, which is cute.
And then I like to read science fiction.
I'm reading a science
fiction book right now
about a trip to Sirius,
which is my next trip.
It's a star that's not
too far away, blue star.
And anyway, it's perro.
It's the dog.
I tried to put the stars.
Imagine that this world
is located at each star
and then imagine that you have been born
in every corner of every planet,
in every square meter of every planet.
MA BYAS PA MA ZAD MI'I RTEN LA
AA MA MA BYAS PA'ANG MED PAS
Not only has everyone been your mother,
everyone's been your mother
just in your human rebirth. Therefore,
SEMS CAN THAMS CAD AA MA
CIS KYANG YIN SNYAM DU BSAM
So it doesn't matter,
AA MA CIS KYANG YIN, it doesn't
matter what they are now.
Insect, virus, elephant,
it doesn't matter.
SNYAM DU BSAM
Think about it, just think about it.
DE LTAR BSAMS KYANG MA SKYES NA
Then it's interesting, he says,
means look, if you do
all this logical flow
I've been teaching you about
mothers and you don't get it,
MA SKYES NA
It's cute, he says, okay,
everything I taught you today, forget it.
If you don't get it, you
don't get it, what the heck?
MA SKYES NA, I got another approach.
I got another choice.
RANG LA MA GTAN NAS MED DAM ZER NA
Then he's, drop your hands
and he says, god damn,
I'm starting to doubt
whether I even had a mother in this life.
Not only you don't get what
I'm trying to tell you,
but you start to doubt your
own mother in this life.
SKYE BA 'DI'I MA MNGON
SUM YOD SNYAM PA 'ONG BAS
He says, go back to your mom in this life.
You don't get all this logic.
It's too complicated for you.
It's giving you a headache.
It's too convoluted. Okay.
Let's go back to basics.
Just go back to your mom in this life.
You had a mom in this life, right?
You can picture her,
maybe she's still alive.
Let's just come back to there.
When this meditation
gets too much for you,
touchstone, go back to the touchstone,
go back to your mom in this life.
You can remember her face.
You can remember beautiful
things she did for you.
Just let's take it back
to your mom in this life.
YOD SNYAM PA 'ONG BAS,
DES SKYE BA 'DI'I SNGA MA
SOGS KYI MA LA SBYAR TE
SPOGS CHOG BYA
Then focus on her having been
the mom in your previous life.
Don't try to see
all living beings have been your mom.
You already have an attachment
to your mom in this life.
So ride that attachment.
Forget all the other living beings.
Forget all the grasshoppers.
Your mom in this life.
- [Male Student] Saltamontes.
- Saltamontes.
If it's too much for you, just
take your mom in this life
and imagine that maybe in a past life,
she was also your mom. You can do that.
That's not so hard.
SBYAR TE SPOGS CHOG BYA
SPOGS here, the word SPOGS means,
RJES DPAG TSAD MA
which means deduction.
This is the verb and it's very unusual, so
SPOGS means, use your logic.
Use your logic, but don't
go to all the insects,
whales and elephants, just go to this mom
and she was your mom before.
Can you handle that?
I can handle that.
I love the next sentence
and it means a lot to me
and we're going to close
with that sentence.
MAR SHES BSGOM TSUL 'DI DAG
Now this method of meditating on MAR SHES.
What's MAR SHES?
Realize, SHES means realize
everyone's been your mom.
MAR SHES BSGOM TSUL 'DI DAG
This whole thing I taught
you in the last two days,
about seeing that people
have been your mom,
it's only presented briefly
in the classical Lam Rims.
And he mentions two of them.
BDE LAM, Path To Bliss,
which, Venerable Gyelse, was written by?
- I'm sorry, I wasn't paying attention.
Nevermind.
First Panchen Lama, 1565 - 1662,
Panchen Lobsang Chukyi Gyelsen,
which is part of the Diamond
Mountain advanced course
for ACI, first three courses.
That Lam Rim, and then
there's a commentary.
There's a Lam Rim which is
like a commentary to it.
Pabongka Rinpoche says,
like a commentary to it,
by his Holiness the Second Panchen Lama,
who is Lobsang Yeshe called MYUR LAM
Which means, quick path, quick path.
He says, look,
if you go to those two classical Lam Rims,
you won't find all these
arguments that I gave you.
They just give a very brief presentation.
Everyone's been your mother, it's logical
and then go on.
He says, so where did this
explanation come from?
BDAG GIS BLA MA'I MDUN DU
DKA' BA SPYAD PA'I LAG RJES
I spent a blank load of hours
learning this from my teacher,
and DKA' BA SPYAD PA means
and I worked my ass off.
It was hard.
DKA' BA SPYAD PA means I worked my ass off
learning this from my lamas,
for year after year,
after year, after year.
LAG RJES means this is just the footprint
of that effort.
The presentation you heard
in the last two sessions
is just the shadow or the sign of the
thousands of hours I
spent learning this stuff
and trying to understand this stuff.
That's just the mere shadow
of the effort I put in.
DKA' BA SPYAD means put in effort.
MAN NGAG LTAR GYI SA BCAD
'DI RGYAS SU BTANG BA YIN PAS
And I've written this presentation.
SA BCAD 'DI means this
presentation or this outline
of the logic for how many moms you've had.
RGYAS SU BTANG BA YIN PAS
I expanded on it based on the
thousands of hours I spent
learning it from great teachers.
I worked hard and I'm
offering it to you, free.
RGYUN DU NYAMS LEN MDZAD MKHAN DANG
If you're a person
who's keeping up their Buddhist
practice pretty steadily,
if you're the kind of person
who's responsible about their practice--
look, nobody's perfect,
you're not keeping your Six Times book,
you're meditating but you're not
keeping your Six Times
book. Or you're doing yoga
but you're not meditating.
Or you're, you know, come on,
when can we do all those things?
But he says, if you're a
pretty steady practitioner
BSTAN PA'I KHUR BZHES PA
This KHUR we discussed in the
Abhidharma class recently,
because it was on an elephant
and it related to the
84,000 heaps of dharma.
KHUR means a load that
you put on an animal.
Sometimes the number of
teachings given by Lord Buddha is defined
as the number of small books
you could load on an elephant
the size of this
building, which is 84,000.
Anyway, that's KHUR.
Here, BSTAN PA'I KHUR BZHES PA.
Are you the kind of person
who is going to take
responsibility to keep
these teachings alive?
Are you going to be an ALL Gold Club?
I don't know what they call it in Mexico.
- Club de Oro
- A Gold Club or a Club de Oro.
Are you going to be the kind of person
who takes responsibility
to make these teachings
survive on this planet?
Are you going to join
all those gold clubs,
and jade clubs, and club-clubs.
And if you're the kind of person
who keeps up a decent practice,
not perfect. And if you're
the kind of person who says,
I'm going to make sure these
teachings stay on this planet.
I take responsibility.
I will raise money in
Guadalajara.
It's tough in Guadalajara.
It's not like New York.
I take responsibility, if
you're that kind of person.
PHYAG LEN
I charge you, I give
you the responsibility,
don't let this teaching get lost.
I worked hard to learn
this from my teachers
and I give you responsibility
to don't let this mom teaching
get lost in the world.
It's very beautiful. He's
like, please, please.
I worked so hard to get it
straight, please keep it.
Take care of it.
This lama will go, that lama will go, but
each generation has to say,
yeah, I'll keep this mom logic.
I'll be the mom logic keeper.
The Gold Club of Guadalajara
will be the mom logic keeper.
I take responsibility.
KHYAD CHE BA YOD means that's a big deal!
That's a big deal, if you guys can do it.
Keep this teaching,
this precious teaching,
keep it well, because--
Then I like the picture,
we can close on the
picture of taking care.
I don't know, me and
Pachi are working on this
carbon sequestering--hey
I remembered the word--
program and it's a big, big thing now.
It's in all the newspapers now.
Suddenly, I never saw sequester
before, now it's everywhere.
Can we take care of these plants
which will store that knowledge?
And that's our responsibility.
And so Pabongka Rinpoche is begging us,
please take care.
Please take responsibility
to take care of this
mom logic teaching.
So you guys, please,
also take responsibility
and we'll see you in the next class.